80 years ago, a war of an unprecedented
scale shook our planet and changed the
face of the world.
Never had war been so widespread, so
brutal,
or so destructive.
A torrent of fire and steel
steeped in [music] courage
and cruelty.
From the Pacific [music] Ocean to the
Mediterranean Sea,
from the deserts of Africa to the
Russian Steppe,
the war broke up nations
and forged [music] empires.
It redefined our borders,
our ideals,
our fears.
The Second World War shaped the world
[music] as we know it.
This is the story of a war that changed
everything.
>> [music]
[music]
>> 1939
World War II was stirring.
It would decide the fate of humankind.
Because the world was a gunpowder keg
threatened by a rising populism.
In the space of 20 years,
no fewer than 15 tyrannical regimes had
been in power.
In the Spain of Franco,
the Italy of Mussolini,
the Hungary of Horthy,
the USSR of Stalin,
or the Japan of Hirohito.
The dictatorships refused the new order
that resulted from World War I
and promised a different future to their
people.
A fascist order.
In Germany, Adolf Hitler, after 6 years
in power, stood out as the figurehead of
totalitarianism.
He set out to build an empire by
dominating Europe and persecuting the
Jews,
whom he cynically blamed for the war he
was preparing.
Danger was rearing its ugly head, but
Europe's democracies favored appeasement
over conflict.
They too were shaken by an upsurge in
extremist movements.
In France and Belgium, the far-right
leagues paraded in the streets.
In the United Kingdom, the British Union
of Fascists was attracting thousands of
new members.
It even appealed to members of the
establishment like the Duke of Windsor.
In New York, 20,000 American
sympathizers yelled, "Heil Hitler!" and
gave the Nazi salute.
A salute which would forever be pregnant
with meaning.
>> [screaming]
>> On the streets, protesters vented their
anger.
>> You all
have heard of me
with the Jewish-controlled press.
>> "Down with Hitler!" yelled Isadore
Greenbaum, a 26-year-old Jewish plumber,
running onto the stage before being
violently restrained.
As the extremist peril escalated, some
tried to raise the alarm.
But their efforts were in vain.
Hitler had already annexed Austria and
occupied Czechoslovakia before turning
his attention to Poland.
This was one step too far.
France and Great Britain promised to
come to Poland's aid if it was attacked.
To avoid having to fight on a second
front, the Führer forged an unlikely
alliance with his ideological enemy,
Joseph Stalin.
The tyrant had ruled as the absolute
master of the Soviet Union for more than
10 years.
He consolidated his power through fear,
imposing a regime that crushed its
opponents in the name of communism.
He, too, dreamed of expansion and wanted
part of Poland.
His pact with Hitler created a new world
order
and would reshape Europe.
For all of its neighbors, the USSR would
remain a threat.
>> Russian military helicopters simply in
Ukrainian airspace.
>> In August of 1939,
Berlin and Moscow signed a
non-aggression pact.
The two dictatorships presented their
unexpected alliance as a desire to
guarantee peace.
On the contrary, it would pave the
[music] way for total war, which would
elevate violence to a planetary scale.
On September the 1st, 1939,
lightning struck Europe.
The Polish cavalry charged.
But the German army crushed it with its
tanks.
Safe in their cockpits, Luftwaffe
bombers dropped their loads.
Warsaw folded under 642 tons of bombs.
Machine gun fire from one German plane
killed the sister of 10-year-old
Kazimiera Mika.
American photographer Julien Bryan
was there to capture the scene.
The only foreign reporter still in
[music] the Polish capital, his
pictures, smuggled out of Europe,
revealed to the rest of the world the
scale of the devastation in Poland.
Marked by a new type of warfare.
Germany had just invented [music] the
Blitzkrieg, the lightning war.
A combination of armored divisions and
aviation
to strike fast and heavily, breaking
through enemy defenses.
It would forever change military
strategy.
In Eastern Poland, the Red Army moved
into the areas which Hitler had conceded
to Stalin.
Sandwiched between the Soviets and the
Germans,
the Polish Army surrendered.
World War II had just begun.
France and Britain had promised to come
to Poland's aid,
but in fact, it was months before they
finally entered the war.
Across the Atlantic, the United States
of America remained isolationist.
The country was yet to become the
world's police force,
and its president, Franklin [music]
Roosevelt, marked by World War I, had
promised to never again sacrifice
American lives in [music] such a distant
conflict.
>> I hope the United States will keep out
of this war.
I believe that it will.
And I give you assurance and reassurance
that every effort of your government
will be directed toward that end.
>> What's more, Roosevelt's concerns were
elsewhere.
His eyes were focused on the Pacific,
where the US had military bases and
trading interests.
Japan, hungry for conquests and
resources, was threatening the stability
of the region.
>> [cheering]
>> 3 years earlier,
Japan had invaded China, first striking
Shanghai, then Beijing.
For the Chinese, this was a time of
historical transformation. [music]
Nationalists and communists, who had
been fighting a civil war for decades,
joined forces to repel [music] the
invasion.
Until then a minority force,
the communists used the conflict to
switch the internal balance [music] of
power.
Armed, trained, and organized [music]
during the war, 10 years later, they
would bring to power the man who changed
the [music] fate of China.
Mao Zedong.
In the meantime, China had become a
quagmire for the Japanese army, which
was swallowed up in the country's
immensity.
From one side of the globe to the other,
the world held its breath.
In Europe, an order believed to be
unshakeable was about to shift.
France, with the world's largest army at
the time, still thought it was protected
by the Maginot Line and took advantage
of the so-called Phoney War to rearm.
After the invasion of Poland, it
mobilized its forces,
working hand in hand with Britain.
200,000 men of the British Expeditionary
Force were sent across the channel to
defend Europe.
But before facing each other directly in
battle, Germans, French, and British
first engaged in economic warfare
with naval blockades, sabotage,
and the control of trade routes.
In Argentina, a German battlecruiser,
which had been hassling British merchant
navy ships for weeks, was forced to
scuttle.
Thousands of kilometers away in Norway,
the Allies attacked a strategic target.
The Germans' iron ore supply, a crucial
material for the manufacture of arms.
Cutting off the enemy's access to
essential resources
was considered the surest path to
victory.
In response, the Germans took the
Blitzkrieg up a gear.
They mobilized 100,000 men on land, sea,
and in the air.
It was the first joint warfare campaign
in history,
combining infantry, navy, and air force.
A logistical feat.
Norway fell in a matter of days. Denmark
in a few hours.
Despite this German show of force, the
French and British, haunted by World War
I, weren't ready to return to the
horrors of the trenches.
So, France mobilized its colonial
regiments, no fewer than 150,000 men to
fight alongside French soldiers in
Europe.
But, the leaders were struggling to
define the objectives of war.
How could they have their men fight
without understanding why?
In May 1940, the Wehrmacht invaded
Belgium and Holland.
The French were finally forced into
action and hurried to the aid of their
allies.
>> With this diversion, German panzers
swept around the Maginot Line and sped
through the Ardennes.
Despite fierce resistance from its
troops, France was on the point of
collapse.
Like Luxembourg, Belgium, and Holland,
it suffered the shame of a lightning
defeat as ruthless as it was unexpected.
These established powers, uncontested
for centuries,
came crashing down.
The trauma [music] was immense.
One single word best resumed the whole
episode. [music]
Debacle.
Towns and cities fell one after the
other.
Hundreds of thousands [music]
of Allied troops fled towards the sea.
The port of Dunkirk became the only
escape route across the channel to
Britain.
>> In London, Winston [music] Churchill was
the newly appointed Prime Minister.
He had seen the Nazi danger approaching
and refused all compromise with [music]
Hitler. Britain entrusted him with its
fate.
He knew that the Battle of France was
lost.
The 400,000 soldiers stranded on the
beaches across the English Channel had
to be saved.
In one of the darkest hours of history,
Churchill kept the light of hope
burning.
He was one of the providential men
forged by World War II and continues to
influence our political imagination
today.
For 10 days, hundreds of British ships
and boats of all sizes braved the waves
to bring home the soldiers who had
retreated to Dunkirk.
A whole country mobilized to come to
their rescue,
pretty much unaware of what awaited
them.
>> [music]
>> Amid strafing from German Stukas, the
men caught in the hell of Dunkirk
desperately struggled to survive.
At sea, Royal Navy Lieutenant [music]
Philip Roderick Hall did his best to
help.
In the air, German pilot Helmut Wick
relentlessly bombed British ships
and finally hit a target.
On shore, French Colonel Jean Marie
saw his last hopes of survival sink into
the harbor.
He was taken prisoner on June the 2nd,
1940 [music]
with 80,000 other soldiers, mostly
French.
Among them,
a large number were from the French
colonies.
These men now knew that France wasn't
invincible.
They had seen defeat with their own eyes
and weren't ready to forget it.
>> The record of coups across Africa
>> For now, Europe was panic-stricken. More
than 10 million Belgians, Danes, Dutch,
and French took to the roads.
The migrants fled southwards hoping to
escape the hordes of German soldiers
[music] sweeping into Western Europe.
A dramatic exodus.
>> Among them were Abraham and Eugenia
Rosenfeld
>> [music]
>> and their 6-year-old son heading for the
south of France.
They had fled from Wuchin, Poland.
In Bordeaux, they stood in line in the
Portuguese Consulate.
Aristides de Sousa Mendes, disobeying
the orders of his government, issued
visas [music] day and night.
He would save 30,000 people,
later earning him the title [music] of
righteous among the nations.
Thanks to this precious opening,
>> [music]
>> the Rosenfelds, like thousands of
others, would soon set sail for America.
Those fleeing persecution in Europe
[music] tried to reach Brazil, the
United States, and even Palestine.
A tragic precedent.
Refugee flows would continue to increase
with each war and natural disaster.
>> Just refugees of the Korean War.
>> On June the 14th, 1940, the French Prime
[music] Minister resigned
and was replaced by Marshal Pétain.
He announced [music] the armistice.
The defeated French helplessly looked on
as the Nazis paraded on their streets.
The defeat would cause a shock wave.
London became the capital of the free
world.
Polish airmen,
French soldiers,
ministers,
kings and queens
from the Netherlands, Norway, or Poland,
politicians who refused defeat,
resolute officers, the stateless accused
of being traitors in their homeland,
gathered there in the hundreds.
Like Charles de Gaulle,
the former Under Secretary of State for
National Defense and War, was determined
to continue the fight.
Exiled in London, on June the 18th, the
Frenchman made his appeal for
resistance.
Although his speech was barely heard in
France,
the rebel made history and forever tied
his fate with that of his homeland.
On the same day as the appeal,
Mussolini met with Hitler in Munich to
discuss how they would share out Europe.
The Führer confided to Il Duce,
"Our interests are in the north,
yours in the south.
Like his ally, Mussolini had dreams of
hegemony.
He wanted to rebuild a Roman Empire to
reign throughout the Mediterranean.
His ambitions were but a mirage.
Italy was ill-prepared for modern
warfare
and totally unable to compete with a
great industrial power like Germany.
But France was on its knees.
On June the 10th, Mussolini took
advantage of its agony to declare war.
The Third Reich, however, only left him
some scraps.
The town of Menton on the French Riviera
and a few Alpine villages.
Hitler claimed the lion's share.
With the armistice between France and
Germany signed,
Petain's government, now installed in
Vichy, would collaborate with the Reich,
which occupied the northern half of
France.
The next day, Hitler paraded through the
streets of Paris.
A photographer and his cortege captured
him in front of the Eiffel Tower,
a symbol of his crushing victory.
Yesterday, a world power, France began
its decline and its colonial empire
wavered. Its colonies in Africa
hesitated between supporting the Vichy
government and resisting it.
While Japan took advantage of France's
defeat to invade Indochina.
The defeats in Europe and the threats in
Asia forced Roosevelt out of his
isolationism.
He was intent on making the United
States the arsenal of democracies to
help them fight back [music] against the
Third Reich and the Empire of the Rising
Sun.
Congress voted for a substantial budget
of 1.3 billion dollars for defense.
American manufacturers transformed
overnight.
Where they had made automobiles,
refrigerators [music] and cameras, they
now produced fighter jets, tanks and
guns.
It was the birth of the
military-industrial complex.
The world center of gravity had shifted.
Great Britain now looked across the
pond.
Breaking with the old continent, it
established a special relationship with
the United States, the future
superpower.
For the time being, the British
enlisted.
250,000 volunteers signed up for the
Home Guard,
encouraged [music] by their hearty Prime
Minister.
>> We shall go on to the end.
We shall fight on the seas and oceans.
We shall defend our island, whatever the
cost may be.
We shall never surrender.
>> Britain prepared for a German invasion.
School children had practice runs to air
raid shelters.
Signposts were taken [music] down to
confuse the enemy.
Airmen were on the front line.
British, ex-pat Belgian, Danish, Polish,
and French pilots
got ready to sacrifice their lives in
the name [music] of freedom.
Facing them, other knights [music] of
the sky,
daredevils like them,
on board their killing machines.
The Luftwaffe was tasked with preparing
the ground for the future invasion
by wiping out British air defenses.
It carried out raids on aircraft
factories and Royal Air Force bases.
For 2 months, a massive aerial battle
was fought for the control of British
skies.
The dogfights approached London.
With the capital on alert, American
reporter Edward Murrow described the
events live.
>> This is Trafalgar Square.
The noise that you hear at the moment
is the sound of the air raid siren.
A searchlight just burst into action off
in the distance.
One single beam sweeping the sky above
me now.
>> It was a first. Across the Atlantic, the
war entered the homes of millions of
listeners.
News in real time would forever change
the role of the media and population's
relation to war.
On September the 7th, the Germans
[music] changed their tactics by
directly targeting British civilians.
An ominous precedent. From then on,
civilians were increasingly caught on
the front lines of warfare.
On September the 7th in the
Mediterranean,
the British colonial empire also came
under attack.
Mussolini ordered his troops to invade
Egypt, then a British protectorate, from
neighboring Libya, then an Italian
colony.
>> [screaming]
>> The British forced back the Italians
[music]
miles from their objective, the Suez
Canal,
the vital artery which linked Britain to
its empire [music] and its resources.
Ignoring this failure, Il Duce opened a
third front without even informing
Hitler.
In Greece this time,
where his troops came up against fierce
national resistance.
Greek pilot Marinos Mitralexos was
caught in a dogfight with an Italian
bomber squadron.
Out of ammunition, he decided one last
throw of the dice and rammed the nose of
his PZL fighter into a bomber's tail.
After an emergency landing, he took
[music] the four Italian crewmen
prisoner.
>> [music]
>> Greek infantrymen were able to hold
their positions thanks to large groups
of women who kept them supplied with
ammunition [music]
carried on their backs.
Pioneers of the role that women [music]
would play in resistance movements all
across Europe.
In Germany, a decisive event would turn
the ongoing conflict into a world war.
>> [music]
>> On September the 27th,
Tokyo joined Rome and Berlin forming an
axis of dictatorships.
All with the same dreams of hegemony.
For the Japanese, Asia.
For the Italians, the Mediterranean and
Africa.
And for the Germans, Europe.
But first, they had to defeat Britain.
The British needed to fold under the
weight of the Blitz.
Made possible by technical advances in
powerful long-distance weaponry,
terror bombings were carried out to
break the enemy's morale
in a form of psychological warfare.
Above the British capital, German pilot
Peter Stahl dropped his bombs.
The explosions reached the ears of
10-year-old Irene Mosley, 20 m
underground.
For 57 nights on the run,
London has sheltered in the depths of
the tube.
Above them, a young British woman, Rosie
Newman, armed with her camera,
captured her people's incredible
resilience.
The British [music] united around their
Prime Minister.
And around the crown,
which protected civilians [music] from
the destruction of the Blitz by
sheltering them, helping them to rebuild
their homes, feeding them, and nursing
them,
heralding the welfare state that would
[music] be established after the war.
Then aged [music] 14,
Princess Elizabeth addressed the
nation's children in a radio broadcast.
>> We are trying to
to bear our own share of the danger and
sadness [music] of war.
We know, every one of us,
that in the end, all will be well.
And when peace comes,
remember,
it will be for us, the children of
today,
to make the world of tomorrow a better
and happier place.
>> It was the first ever public speech by
she who would go on to rule the United
Kingdom for more than 70 [music] years,
lastingly marked by the experience of
war.
Despite 15,000 lives lost, the Blitz
failed to break British morale.
Especially as Britain could now count on
growing American support.
In September 1940, a British scientific
delegation crossed the Atlantic carrying
precious industrial secrets in an
attaché case.
These were key military technologies
destined for the United States.
The resources and support provided by
Washington
paved the way [music] for unprecedented
cooperation.
Radar, sonar, light and [music] heavy
weaponry, this strategic sharing
resulted in phenomenal progress [music]
which would change the course of the
war.
The United Kingdom wouldn't go down
without a fight.
The British even met with several
successes in Africa.
In Libya, but also in Ethiopia and
Eritrea,
they forced back Mussolini's troops.
They were on the point of expelling the
Italians from Africa.
But just as victory seemed imminent,
Churchill decided to transfer 60,000 of
his soldiers in Africa to aid the Greek
army.
A huge mistake which deprived him of
immediate victory.
Because the humiliated Mussolini begged
aid from the Third Reich,
and Hitler dispatched his soldiers.
A German expeditionary force, the Africa
Corps, commanded by General Rommel,
arrived to support Italy in Libya.
Then the German army invaded Greece,
which succumbed within 3 weeks.
On their way to Greece, the Germans had
also broken Yugoslavia, which had dared
to side [music] with Britain.
Bulgaria and Romania joined the
Rome-Berlin Axis.
Save a few countries, the swastika flew
above the whole of Europe.
There was nothing now to prevent the
Führer from looking eastwards.
From the USSR, Stalin looked on
helplessly as the Nazi empire was built.
He considered the Balkans to be his
turf, and now the Germans were camped at
his door.
It was a pivotal moment. If Hitler
attacked, he would force the Soviets
onto his enemy's side.
Stalin remained convinced that the
Führer wouldn't be crazy enough to break
their pact and open a new front in the
east while he was still fighting
Britain.
And when General Zhukov, the
second-in-command of the Red Army,
demanded that his troops be placed on
red alert,
Stalin was against it.
"Germany will never attack Russia," he
affirmed.
Hitler proved him wrong.
He dispatched his troops to take the
Russian steppe.
A gigantic [music] operation.
Five and a half million soldiers, 3,710
tanks, 4,980
aircraft were mobilized across a front
[music] 2,000 km wide.
This was Operation Barbarossa,
the largest military invasion in World
War II.
Stalin was distraught, but tried to get
his country ready for war.
He had one objective, a war of
extermination.
It was no longer a matter of conquering
territories, but of annihilating entire
peoples,
and reducing communist ideology to
ashes.
This was the starting point of an
escalation of horror and cruelty which
would haunt humankind.
On June the 27th, 1941,
at the controls of his tank,
Oberleutnant Friedrich Sander advanced
across the steppe.
In his path, a wounded Russian soldier
stood up and waved.
The pitiless Sander accelerated and
crushed him to death.
The Soviet cities fell.
Smolensk, Minsk, and then Kiev.
Hundreds of thousands of soldiers
[music] surrendered.
The German [music] troops starved,
extenuated, tortured, or executed Soviet
prisoners.
Well to the rear,
the Einsatzgruppen, or execution squads,
massacred Jews.
>> At Babi Yar near Kiev,
more than 33,000 men, women, and
children,
guilty only of being born,
were slaughtered in a vast ravine.
This massacre would become known as the
Holocaust of bullets.
It set the precedent of a process that
nobody was yet able [music] to imagine.
The systematic genocide of Europe's
Jews.
In 200 days,
more than 5 million Soviets were killed.
Hitler predicted that the war would be
over by December.
The USSR was on the brink of defeat.
A lesson that its leaders never forgot.
Never again [music] would they leave
their territory open to invasion.
And all conquests close to its borders
would become a shield. Even today,
Russia has maintained this paranoid
[music] fixation to protect itself
behind a defensive glassier.
For now,
panic overcame the Russian capital.
Especially after Stalin ordered the
evacuation of the embassies [music] and
main government offices.
But the master of the Kremlin instilled
calm once he announced he would be
staying [music] in the city.
Moscow would be defended.
But at what price?